<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lamentable newes, shewing the wonderfull deliuerance of Maister Edmond Pet sayler and maister of a ship, dwelling in Seething Lane in London, neere Barking church. With other strange things lately hapned concerning these great windes and tempestuous weather, both at sea and lande.</title>
            <title>Lamentable newes, shewing the wonderfull deliverance of Maister Edmond Pet sayler.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4792</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09512)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4792)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 857:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lamentable newes, shewing the wonderfull deliuerance of Maister Edmond Pet sayler and maister of a ship, dwelling in Seething Lane in London, neere Barking church. With other strange things lately hapned concerning these great windes and tempestuous weather, both at sea and lande.</title>
                  <title>Lamentable newes, shewing the wonderfull deliverance of Maister Edmond Pet sayler.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T. C[reede] for William Barley, dwelling ouer against Cree-church, neere Algate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Great losses by sea and land.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pet, Edmond.</term>
               <term>Storms --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4792:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4792:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LAMENTABLE Newes, Shewing the wonderfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance of Maiſter Edmond Pet Sayler, and Maiſter of a Ship, dwelling in Seething Lane in London, neere Barking Church. With other ſtrange things late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hapned concerning theſe great windes and tempeſtuous wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, both at Sea and Lande.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>two men in a ship, drawing something from the water</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>T.C.</hi> for William Barley, dwelling ouer againſt Cree-church, neere Algate. 1613.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4792:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4792:2"/>
            <head>LAMENTABLE newes shewing the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull deliuerance of M. Edmond Pet Sailer and Maiſter of a ſhip, dwelling in Seething Lane in London, neare Barking Church. With <hi>other ſtrange things, lately happened, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the great winds and tempestuous weather both at Sea and</hi> Land.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, I haue here ſet downe vnto thy view, and for thy example to amendment, the great hurt and loſſes that hath béene both at Sea and Land, but eſpecially the wonderfull preſeruation of one Maiſter <hi>Edmond Pet</hi> Sayler, and Maiſter of a ſhip, and part owner, who was comming from New Caſtle with his Ship lading, and with diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the ſhip, both paſſengers, and his owne ſeruants: griefe to tell, as it is well knowne, and too well, if it had bene Gods will to the contrarie, the wind being ruffe and furious, cauſed the Seas to be outragious and boyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and the waues thereof to be ſo great, and to ariſe ſo hie, that many times they were readie to ouerwhelme the ſhip, yet by Gods prouidence &amp; the great care of this Maiſter <hi>Pet</hi> being Maiſter, and ſore labour and earneſt
<pb facs="tcp:4792:3"/> praier vnto the Lord, night and day of thoſe in the ſhip, they were preſerued vntill they came within the kenning of Land, both of <hi>Yearmouth</hi> and <hi>Harwich,</hi> and other townes, but ſtill the wind did growe more ſtrong, and the waues greater, and euery one ouertyred with ſore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as ſome at the pumpe, and ſome otherwaies, not one hauing leaſure or ſtomacke almoſt either to eat or drinke, ſo that then they did wholy relie vpon Gods mercy, cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from their labours, and then did this Maiſter <hi>Pet</hi> make a godly ſpéech: ſaying vnto the reſt, <q> Let vs all knéele downe with earneſt praier, and euen with the knées of our hearts, deſire God for his deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to deliuer vs from this great danger, crying all with loud and wofull voyces, O Lord preſerue vs now, that we may liue and honour thée in prayſing thy name with Pſalmes of thankeſgiuing, as thou didſt preſerue <hi>Ionas</hi> thrée daies in the maine Seas, and in the belly of a mightie deuouring Whale, and chaſt <hi>Suſanna</hi> from the wicked Elders, who would haue diſhonoured God in their luſt, and brought to deſtruction that godly woman and chaſt wife. Likewiſe O Lord, thou didſt preſerue thy ſeruant <hi>Daniel</hi> from the gréedie iawes of the cruell and rauenous Lyons, being of purpoſe kept hungry in their dennes. O good Lord thou didſt make the blind to ſée, the halt and lame to goe, and the dead to ariſe and walke, ſo good Lord if it be thy bleſſed will, thou canſt now deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, euen now when all mans helpe is paſt. </q> And now in this ſpace while Maiſter <hi>Pet</hi> was vſing theſe ſpéeches, and earneſt prayer to God, the ſhip began to ſinke déeper and déeper into the Sea, whereupon euery one began to ſhift for himſelfe in laying hold ſome vpon one thing, and ſome vpon another. As they were ſtanding vpon the hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſtill called on God, but ſéeing there was no way to ſaue themſelues, then with great ſhrikes and loud cries they were al drowned: Nay more, not one liuing thing in the ſhip ſaued. And Maiſter <hi>Edmond Pet,</hi> after he had
<pb facs="tcp:4792:3"/> bene vnder water, by Gods helpe tooke hold of the maine Maſt and got out his knife and cut certaine cords or lines and made ſhift to get vp to the top of the Maſt, and there tied himſelfe, for feare leaſt by the ſtrength of the winde &amp; rain, he ſhould be blowne off into the Sea. All which this man in miſerie did ſée, and himſelfe looking euery minute of an houre to taſte of the ſame cup the reſt had done: for now halfe the maine Maſt whereon he ſate was couered with water, this being about ſeuen of the clocke in the morning. Thus ſat this grieued man all that day and all night, ſéeing nothing but water readie to ſwallow him vp: yet vpon the next day, betwéene the houres of ſeuen and eight of the clocke, to his great comfort, he deſcried a ſhip comming towards him, he being beaten ſo ſore with winde and weather, that he could hardly ſpeake, for his body was ſwelled as bigge as two bodies, and likewiſe his legges did grow to ſuch a bignes, that they were more like to the waſte or middle of a man, then the legge of a man, yet when this ſhip came neare vnto him, he cryed and called as well as he could, that they would ſaue him, and take him into their ſhip. One or two of them anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red very briefly, we are ſorrie, we are ſorrie, but we cannot ſtay. O moſt vnkind men, and in humane, that euer man ſhould haue cauſe to ſay, that euer any Chriſtian ſhould be ſo hard-harted to leaue a man in that diſtreſſe. But when he ſaw them ſaile away, Oh! it was more then halfe a killing to his poore heart. Well when he had ſat on this maine Maſt vntill the next morning, which was 48. houres, there came towards him by Gods appoyntment a man of warre, being a <hi>Hollander,</hi> who did ſhew him kindnes and mercy, for he did ſend his ſhip-boate for him, and brought him to his ſhip, and did ſeeke to comfort him in what he could, like the good <hi>Samaritane,</hi> but this Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Pet</hi> was ſo weather beaten, and ſo ſwelled, that he could neither eate nor drinke: yet this man of warre would and did what he could for him, for ſéeing he could
<pb facs="tcp:4792:4"/> not comfort him with any thing he had in his ſhip, he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into a towne in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> called <hi>Harwich,</hi> and there ſt him on ſhore, not leauing him vntill he had brought him to ſome of his old acquaintance, who did not knowe him: nay more, his owne wife did not knowe him, when he was brought home to <hi>London,</hi> by reaſon he was ſwelled of ſuch bignes, and ſo changed with ſitting, as I tolde you before 48. houres in the winde &amp; raine. And ſee and heare and giue God praiſe; yet more of Gods wonderfull kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in deliuering this Maiſter <hi>Pet</hi> once before, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from a farre voyage in a Ship of Marchandiſe, by miſfortune the Ship was ſplit, the Ship and all the goods loſt, and to the number of eightéene perſons drowned. And this man left aliue to tell vnto the world what God had done for him, that all that heare it might praiſe the Lord: and praiſed be the name of the Lord, he is now well and in perfect health. And as I ſaid before, dwelling in Séething Lane in <hi>London.</hi> Wel now leauing this ſad ſtorie of Maiſter <hi>Pet,</hi> with griefe I muſt tell you, of others harmes and loſſes: Firſt there was to the great terror and griefe of many the beholders, ſixe ſcore dead men taken vp, vpon <hi>Yarmouth</hi> ſhore, the loſſes of Boates and Lyters, and men lately vpon the Thames, is too well knowne, if it had béene Gods will to haue bene other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, for many haue ſéene dead men ſwimming too and fro betwéene <hi>Graues End</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> being carried by the Tyde, and ſtill hats or cloakes, and ſtaues, and diuers other things of Paſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers haue ſeene bene vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Thames ſwimming too and fro, &amp; a great Barge being laden with fagots and billets, and other timber to make cartwhéeles, was caſt away néere <hi>London</hi> bridge, being in a ſtorme of winde, and all her lading ſwimming vp and downe the Thames. Likewiſe neare the coaſt of <hi>Douer</hi> &amp; <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Wayborne Hoope</hi> in <hi>Norfolke,</hi> was much hurt done, with the loſſe of many mens liues. Likewiſe all the vpper parts of a windmill in <hi>Bedfordſhire</hi> was blowne
<pb facs="tcp:4792:4"/> away, but God be praiſed none kild. Neare <hi>Sharnbrook,</hi> a traueller of <hi>London</hi> that came downe to ſée his friends, was by the ſtrength of the winde blowne off from a bridge, but by others was taken vp aliue and ſaued. Two men and their horſes in <hi>Gloſterſhire</hi> were blowne from a bridge, &amp; both horſe and men drowned. A man neere <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> being thatching a houſe, was blowne off &amp; kild: trées blowne vp by the rootes, other reſt and torne, houſes and chimnies quite blowne downe, falling vpon cattell &amp; kild them, to the great loſſe and hurt of many men. And diuers other ſtrange matters I could ſpeake of, all which is for our ſinnes. God grant we way take warning to amend our liues by theſe dangers &amp; loſſes, or elſe we muſt néeds looke for farther puniſhment. For as God is mercifull, ſo he is Iuſt, and will puniſh vs if we will not be warned by theſe examples. God grant for his Sonne Ieſus Chriſts ſake we may all be warned to amend our liues. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
